This is Hacker Public Radio Episode 4731, for 2026-09-21
Today's show is entitled, "A Website Hacked"
The host is Lee and the duration is 00:13:48
The flag is Clean, and the license is CC-BY-SA
The summary is "About an encounter with wp2shell that was not so bad"
Hi, I'm Lee. This is the story of the website getting hacked.
The first is the story of the website itself.
The website belongs to a charity. The organized farmers' markets once a month,
also several sessions each week of inclusive cycling at local track named after a
Paralympic athlete who won gold medals when the Olympics was hosted here.
There were also a few sessions a week for community food grind and various other things.
The website was originally hosted by the same company the domain name was bought from.
VAs the charity would pay a lot for SSL stiff cuts and full website hosting.
That year as I'd go, the DNS got screwed up, apparently because they were transferring
hosting to a different day to centre.
And when I called the support line, they were completely unable to tell me the IP address
of the server the website was currently on.
I suggested to the charity that they cut their losses and temporarily let me
set up a VPS and migrated there until it was actually time as a new hosting
provided we found.
Since the website was on WordPress, it was soon possible to find some very good
value WordPress hosting for more reliable provider.
The SSL stiff cut was no longer a problem as it was included for no extra cost.
Anyway, that was a year or so ago so it then got migrated there.
My great and WordPress site can be as simple as backing up then restoring the database
copying the files to the new server and plugging in some configuration values
to match the new environment.
For this task I'd be using PHP, my admin to grab the SQL and possibly follow ZL to copy files.
In practice things could get more complicated, sometimes various database tables
might need updating, especially if the domain name was different.
There are lots of tools and plugins to help with this.
Often in the past I'd just be writing my own PHP script to grab back-ups
over HTDPS, especially since the provider that used to host the website
has some kind of throttling limits on FTP downloads.
While in the early days of this website there was a lot of interventionated.
It's actually been running apparently smoothly for some time,
and performing much better with the new hosts.
In retrospect I guess the server upgrades are led to the problems that sort of squit the old provider
or most likely in attempt by them to improve their performance to something acceptable.
Anyway, now that the website does it say no to our dates with little technical maintenance required,
the users can just log in and focus on updating content.
One considerable change of the years has been going back to using the built-in editor
rather than plugins that improve the editing experience at the expense of adding layers of complexity.
WordPress is modern editor is called the block editor,
and it's just that a way of composing pages from a sequence of blocks,
including ones that can contain other blocks.
To me this is a big improvement from a simplicity and usability perspective once you get how it works.
In terms of referring all the tricks people would have to go to make things look right from the task of actually producing content.
Another recent improvement of WordPress that have not really looked into too much myself
is that you can now edit what you see rather than having to work out what level of the presentation the thing you want to edit is that.
For example, is it a fixed header that is global to the whole website?
Or is it something specific to a particular page?
Now it does not matter so much whichever it is when you try to edit it the system adapts to let you.
I might be able to stay in these improvements in some ways that there to address fundamental issues with dynamic content management systems like WordPress.
These are, they're almost slightly because the management code runs alongside the presentation code.
They're cashing helps with that somewhat.
Anything style code in online text editors, it definitely leads to confusion of purpose between what you want to say and how you want to style and present it.
What you see is not what you get because the final presentation is built from very schematic and presentation or layers.
On a subject of style, what you can choose to template that defines the overall look and feel of your site.
I've always found this needed tweaking for particular purposes you need to what the stateholders required from the site.
Luckily WordPress has a custom CSS area where this can be sorted.
The last bit of work along these lines we're mentioning was set in an up and up valid dark made for the site.
Another thing about WordPress in particular that partly true of other content management systems is that there are thousands of plugins.
If you can think of a particular functionality in my one or a service that you might want to integrate website with, there's probably a plugin or two or three for that.
The disadvantage of making the system so general purpose that fits every use case is that you end up exposing the full complexity of the underlying system.
If something does one thing well, it is generally easy to minimize the attack surface.
That is the number of possible ways something external could interact with it in a malicious way.
But when a system does so many possible things it inevitably has many vulnerabilities.
They can as a whole the WordPress ecosystem, which I guess includes plugins and such, has about 35,000 known issues in counting in the common vulnerabilities and exposure state base.
So for the character's website to get hacked, it took just two of these CVA 2026 6030 and CVA 2026 60137 been exploited together in a new way called by the smart folks who think of exploit names WP to shell.
And it was not just this website but hundreds and thousands all across the interwebs.
The first thing on your bet any of this was an email from the hosting provider, urging users to quickly apply patch that would seal this hole.
I complied it was just a matter of manually tain WordPress to update a minor version and it was done.
But the trouble is just because you've sealed a hole, it does not mean the boat has not run to take an unwater.
A week later the hosting provider got in touch again, they said they had evidence that something or other had been modified or accessed by to the patch being applied.
This sounded bad, it could be the site was infected with scripts then who knows what mischief.
The provider recommended rolling the site back by a week and a half to before the malicious access occurred.
Then immediately reapplying the security patch this time making sure nothing had been tampered with.
However before blindly abaying I thought I checked with the charity manager.
As I suspected the staff were busy with the run up to the big fan next month.
Over a hundred stalls potentially 10,000 visitors.
There was potentially a lot of data that had been input recently that would be lost if I rolled back.
So I suggested I take a good look and see what exactly the damage was to the site.
My first step was to take an offline backup of the database.
As I mentioned before I used PHP my admin's export feature for this.
I used the 200 megabyte SQL script tip produced to populate my own instance of MariaDB so I could query it will without affecting the life site.
I also SSHed into the web space tied the contents folder and then GZPed it to a folder on my hard disk.
In that tab all were 2.9 gigabytes of files including both media and the scripts that comprise the running system itself.
This was not just for forensic purposes but downloads could potentially be used to restore articles and media even if the rollback turned out to be necessary.
And while I know my way around work presses internal structure somewhat having written my own plugins for example.
I did not want my humanized to miss anything important.
So I asked the cloud based LLM coding tool to produce both the database and downloaded files.
Firstly I was able to check that each of the users on the system could be accounted for.
So no new users had been added.
Also there was no strange or unusual session activity for those users.
Then the various site options were examined.
The sort of things people generally customize those all seem normal too.
Then the contents of the site itself the posts and pages all were true to topic and like hidden payloads.
Finally the scope of damage was discovered and it was mainly linked to data revisions and as customized change set posts.
And these changes were not even live and only contained dummy URLs.
There was also some innocuous activities to do with caching in the OEM bed cache a few day subsequent to the first access.
The first changes happened in the early hours.
A week and a half ago just as the webposting for 500 hinted up.
They had been entered with four-jump administrative level access.
Not for an actual real login.
A trick had been used to lay a one exploit on another and get access.
There would be otherwise impossible.
Almost certainly there's been done by an automated script.
Scanning thousands of websites making a small change on any that it could.
And recording which ones it had been able to compromise so that someone potentially then actually do something more malicious later on.
It's like a trespass so who on first entry just messes with the position of objects on your desk a little.
Stealing nothing but noting the properties of potential future target.
The next finding was more reassuring.
None of the script files of the WordPress system itself were anything but themselves.
No hidden secrets.
They all matched exactly their checksum.
An episode I was recently listening to.
HPR 4677 by Varns.
Talked about what checksums and hashes are.
And they certainly helped in this case.
Another post-defining was that all the plugins and themes were as they should be.
No rogue ones had been added.
Also the.ht access file.
Often used for redirecting traffic was untouched.
Then something a little worrying.
A list into I realized what it was.
There were two scripts.
One for listing the files and one for downloading the contents of any file.
And this sounds quite bad.
After all it made hackers had probably got sensitive info such as database passwords and someone.
But then I realized.
These scripts were ones I put there myself the last time I migrated the site.
I just hadn't removed them.
At least I had.
But I forgot that they had included themselves in their own backup.
And so got restored along with the rest of the site after it was migrated.
Thankfully security by obscurity.
The worst kind of security.
Had been no one knew about these scripts.
They had not been exploited.
I made a note to remove them as soon as my investigation was complete.
There's just one other rogueish looking page piece grip lurking in there.
This was quickly identified to be a left over from some word press installer.
And in and of itself it was harmless.
Notably the mitigation script that patched the vulnerability was noted to be present.
So my investigation was over.
It was not necessary to use a sledgehammer where screw driver sufficed.
The charity did not have to lose a week and a half of day trend tree.
And the run-up to an important event.
So hopefully the website will be there providing use of information.
And the run-up to the big fair next month.
I wrapped things up while changing my administrative password just in case.
And it froze the manch of the charity.
It was the only other administrators to do the same.
Given though that theory this has wrapped up the issue.
It would be sensible to continue to monitor things fairly closely for a while.
Just in case something was missed.
I thought that was that perhaps.
At the next day another community group that organised an annual lavender pick had
the same warning from the same provider.
Given the harvest when ahead of this last weekend, the website was now far low.
So they decided to take the easier way and just let the provider roll back.
Then their site could be re-patched.
And finally password's changed just to be thorough.
Hopefully an exploit is pervasive as WP2 shell.
Something that comes along only rarely.
But with AI large language models being used to both create exploits in defend against them.
Who knows?
The provider hosting both the sites are mentioned by no means unique in having this instant effect.
It was a worldwide event.
And there was once in practically no defined users providing an easy roll back was
Lordable.
Finally enough I had been noticing unusual wordpress style probes.
And the logs of some of myself hosted static sites.
They did not even run a wordpress in the run up to this happening.
And I shrugged it off with random internet noise.
But I don't know if that activity was related to this.
In terms of security in general, the fence and depth at various levels
Not assuming anyone barriers foolproof is probably the best approach.
Especially if risk and potential impact of the breaches high.
I think web application firewalls can help to some extent to mitigate some attacks like this.
And I've dabbled with these back in the days when I had my own virtual private server.
Having a clean backup and monitoring for suspicious activity adjusters important
as applying the constant stream of security patches,
though most every significant software product nowadays needs.
Anyway, all of security the story never ends for now is upside-dust.
Thanks for listening.
You have been listening to the Hacker Public Radio podcast, at hackerpublicradio.org.
Today's show was contributed by a HPR listener like yourself.
If you ever thought of recording a podcast, then visit the HPR site to find out how easy it really is.
Hosting for HPR has been kindly provided by anhonesthost.com, the Internet Archive, rsync.net, and the HPR Community Content Delivery Network.
Unless otherwise stated, today's show is released under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0) license.